嘿，大家好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno and welcome back to my OpenGL series
现在，我很兴奋，终于有时间做这个系列了
now, I'm so excited to finally get around to doing this series
所以，在过去的两期里，就是这个系列最初的两期
so, over the last two episodes, which kind of the first two episodes of the series
事实上，我们只是在搞一些配置，比如配置OpenGL和GLEW
we really just were setting things up, and we were setting up OpenGL and GLEW
基本上能够在OpenGL窗口中绘制图形我们需要的所有配置
and basically everything we needed to be able to draw graphics in an OpenGL window
并且现在，它终于设置好了，所以我们可以开始运行一些OpenGL代码了
and now, that's finally set up, so we can start running some OpenGL code
现在，我知道，不过我还是保持这样说，我只需要再次声明一下
now, I know, I keep saying this, but I just want to say it one more time
我们没有在开发游戏引擎，这个系列，我们只是学习OpenGL
we're not making a game engine, we're just learning OpenGL here
这就是为什么我不厌其烦地这样说
which is why I'm not going to bother like doing this properly so to speak
我只是想让你们看看，实际上, 你们需要写什么样的OpenGL代码才会实现这些
I'm just interested in showing you guys, what OpenGL code you actually need to write to make things happen
你们要如何抽象那些代码，比如把它们抽象到类里面去，并且所有这些都是你们要做的
how you choose to abstract that, and kind of move it into like classes and all of that that's your business
当然，当游戏引擎系列出来时，很快就会出来了，对吧，我们会讲到那些的
and certainly, when the game engine series comes out, it's gonna be very soon, wink, we're gonna cover that
所以，记住这一点，别指望
anyway, so, just keep that in mind, don't expect
这是指导你们应该如何开发一个游戏引擎，或者应该如何使用OpenGL开发一款游戏
this is how you should write a game engine, or how you should make a game using OpenGL
这只是教你们，在绘图时需要写什么样的OpenGL代码，以及它的原理
this is just what OpenGL code you need to write to make graphics happen, and how it works
所以, 现代OpenGL比那种传统OpenGL更具有可编程性
so the thing with modern OpenGL is that it's very programmable much more than the legacy kind of OpenGL
它的拓展性更好，也更加强大，你们能用它做许多事情，结果就是
it's pretty extensive, it's fairly powerful, there's a lot you can do with it, and as a result
在屏幕上绘制一个三角形之前，你们实际上需要做很多设置
there is quite a lot of setup you actually need to do before you can see a triangle on the screen
实际上，这是我们之前已经做了的，并且我认为就是在我们设置GLFW的第一期中
now what we did in the last few episodes in fact, and I think the first episode where we set up GLFW is
我们就使用了传统OpenGL，只用了glBegin()和glEnd()在屏幕上绘制一个三角形
we just used like legacy OpenGL, we just use glBegin() glEnd() to draw a triangle on the screen
因为就是那五行代码，而且你们已经做过了，这就是个三角形
because that is like five lines of code and you're done, here's a triangle
传统OpenGL做起来很容易，并且不需要什么设置
it's easy to just do and it requires no setup
然而，使用现代OpenGL去画一个三角形，需要做一些事情
however, to draw a triangle using modern OpenGL, a few things need to happen
首先，我们需要能够创建一个顶点缓冲区，然后还要创建一个着色器
primarily, we need to be able to create a vertex buffer, and we need to also be able to create a shader
现在, 我正在计划将来不久做一期视频
now, I am planning to make a video soon in the future
讲一下图形渲染管线是如何运行的
that's just going to cover kind of how graphics pipelines work
特别是OpenGL的图形渲染管线是如何运行的，所以我们现在不会讲太多
and specifically how the OpenGL graphics pipeline works, so we're not going to get into that too much
所以，还是让我们先说说，现在需要什么东西才能用现代OpenGL绘制一个三角形
but let's talk about, what we need now to draw a triangle in modern OpenGL
因为在电脑上渲染的图形都是从三角形开始的
because every piece of graphics that we can possibly render on our computer begins with triangle
所以，下面就是我们所需要的两个东西，对吧
so I mentioned two things that we really need here, right
我们需要顶点缓冲区和着色器，让我们快速地说一下这两个东西是什么吧
we need a vertex buffer and we need something called a shader, let's talk about what that even is just quickly
那么，顶点缓冲区，它基本上就是去掉vertex这个单词
so, a vertex buffer it's basically just just get rid of the word vertex
从它的名字里去掉vertex这个单词
because it's just get rid of the…the word vertex from that
它只是一个缓冲区，一个内存缓冲区，一个内存字节数组，那是它的本质，只是个缓冲区
it's just a buffer, it's a memory buffer, it's an array of bytes of memory, that's what it is, it's just a buffer
我的意思是从字面上来说
and what I mean by that is it's literally like
它就是一块用来存字节的内存，存字节的，明白吗
a blob of memory in which we can kind of push bytes, bytes into there, right
并且这个想法当然是因为它与OpenGL绑定
and the idea is of course because it's tied with OpenGL
但顶点缓冲区跟C++中像字符数组的内存缓冲区不太一样
it's not just a buffer of memory like as if I just created a char array or something in C++
并且你们也知道的，那只是内存上的缓冲区, 对吧
and you know, that's a that's a buffer of memory, right
区别在于, 它是OpenGL中的内存缓冲区
the difference is that this is a buffer of memory in OpenGL
这意味着它实际上在显卡上，在我们的VRAM(显存)中，也就是Video RAM
which means it's actually in our GPU, in our VRAM, our Video RAM
所以这里的基本思路就是，我要定义一些数据来表示三角形
so the basic concept here is, I want to define a bunch of data which represents my triangle
我要把它放入显卡的VRAM中，然后还需要发出DrawCall指令
I want to put it into my GPU's VRAM, and then I want to issue something called a DrawCall
这是一个绘制指令，就是说
which is basically a draw command, which says
嘿，你的显存中有一堆数据
hey, you know that bunch of that blob of data you've got there in your VRAM
读取它，并且把它绘制在屏幕上，实际上，我们还需要告诉显卡
read from it, and draw it on the screen, and furthermore we actually need to tell our GPU
如何读取和解释这些数据，以及如何把它放到我们屏幕上
how to read and interpret that data, and how to actually put it onto our screen
当我们在CPU这边做了所有的事情
because, once we kind of do everything from the cpu side
我们用C++写的东西都是在CPU上运行的，对吧
everything we write in C++ is just done on the CPU, right
当我们写完这些东西，还要用某种方法告诉显卡
once we've written all of that stuff, we also need to somehow tell the graphics card
一旦从CPU发出了DrawCall指令，一旦我们发出那个指令
once we issue that DrawCall which does come from the CPU, once we issue that DrawCall
我们就要告诉显卡，好了
we need to actually tell the GPU, okay
一旦你从显卡读到了这些数据
once you interpret, once you get access to that data on the GPU side
我要你像那样把它绘制出来，我希望你在屏幕上给我显示一个三角形
I want you to lay it out like that, I want you to draw me and pasteurize me a triangle on the screen
所以我们需要告诉显卡它要做什么，所以需要对显卡编程，并且，那就是着色器
so we need to tell the GPU what to do, so we need to program the GPU, and that's what a shader is
着色器是一个运行在显卡上的程序，是一堆我们可以编写的可以在显卡上运行的代码
a shader is just a program that runs on the GPU, it's a bunch of code that we can write which runs on the GPU
它可以在显卡上以一种非常特殊又非常强大的方式运行，这个我们以后再探究
and in a very specific way and in a very powerful way which, which we can explore in the future
但那基本上是可以消化的，不要想太多
but that's basically digestive, don't overthink it too much
我们有一堆可以指定的内存，对吧，一堆我要指定的数据
we just basically have a bunch of memory that we can specify, right, a bunch of data that I can specify
告诉显卡，嘿，这是数据，然后显卡那边响应，好吧, 现在读取一下这些数据
tell the GPU, hey, here's data, and then from the GPU side say, okay, now read this data
而且好像可以理解成是屏幕上的位置，然后把它们连成一个三角形
and interpret it as like a bunch of positions on your screen maybe,  and join them up into a triangle
那就是这整个的原理，那就是
that's kind of how this whole thing works, and that is the
我想这就是所有这些OpenGL渲染代码的基础功能吧
I guess the foundation the basics of all of this kind of OpenGL rendering code
就像我刚才描述的那样，有一些数据，然后给我绘制出来
it's just what I've just described there, have some data, then draw me something
有个很重要的点需要注意，OpenGL具体的操作就是一个状态机
now it's it's really important to note that,  OpenGL specifically operates as a state machine
也就是说你们不需要把它看成对象或类似的东西
what that means is that you don't necessarily treat it like an object or anything like that
你们所做的是设置一系列的状态，然后当你们说一些事情
what you do instead is you set a series of states, and then when you say something
比如，给我绘制个三角形，那是与上下文相关的
like hey draw me a triangle, that's very contextual
我的意思，不是我说“嘿，给我绘制个三角形”之后
what I mean by that is instead of me just saying hey draw me a triangle
然后才传给OpenGL绘制三角形所需要的东西
and then passing in everything that OpenGL needs to draw the triangle
实际上，它已经知道了它绘制三角形所需要的东西，因为那是状态的一部分
it actually knows already what it needs to draw the triangle, because that's part of the state
所以换句话说，可以这么说，我想让你选择这个缓冲区
so to put it another way, you basically say I want you to select this buffer
用这个着色器，然后给我绘制个三角形
I want you to select this shader and then draw me a triangle
对吧，然后根据你选择的缓冲区和着色器
right, and based on which buffer and which shader you've selected
决定绘制什么样的三角形，绘制在哪里等等
that's what's going to determine what triangle gets drawn and where and all of that stuff
那就是OpenGL的原理，它是一个状态机
that's how OpenGL works, it's a state machine
那样很烦，事实上，可能确实很烦人，但那就是它的运行方式
that can be annoying, in fact it probably is annoying, but that's just how it operates
通常来说，学习和了解这些对OpenGL很重要，所以，记在心里
learning that and just knowing that is just very important for OpenGL in general, so keep that in mind
说完这些要记住的东西后，我想让这个系列更多一些实践
and so with all of that in mind, I do want to keep this series a little bit more practical
那么，让我们来写一些代码创建顶点缓冲区，看看我们能做些什么，好了
so let's just write some code to create this vertex buffer, and see what we can do with that, okay
那么，这是我们在第一期中写的代码
so what we have here is what we kind of wrote in the first episode
也就是通过指定三个顶点来画三角形，对吧
which was this basic triangle that we drew by specifying three vertices, right
我们用的是比较简单的传统OpenGL
and we did this by using legacy OpenGL which was very easy to do
我们想用现代OpenGL来画这个，那么就要创建顶点缓冲区
What we now want to do to basically draw this, according to modern OpenGL is create vertex buffer
顶点缓冲区包含这些顶点的数据，就是这些数据
which just contains, well, this data, there it is that's our data
我们把它放进一个缓冲区，传到OpenGL的VRAM
We just want to actually put that into a buffer, send it to OpenGL's VRAM
然后，发出一个DrawCall指令，说，嘿，请根据缓冲区画出图形
and then later, issue a DrawCall saying: hey, draw my buffer please
要做到这一点，我们肯定要到while循环的外面，这是gl循环，对吧
So to do that, we're definitely going to want to go outside of our while loop, this is just our gl's loop, right
我们不想在每一帧都这样做
we don't want to be doing this every single frame
我们可以先定义一个缓冲区，然后填入数据
we can just define a buffer to begin with and then we can actually fill it with data
然后在gl渲染循环中，我们就可以说，嘿，绘制已经存在的数据
and then inside gl's render loop, we can just say: hey, draw the data that already exists
如果出于某一些原因，我们需要改变数据帧或者其他东西
if for some reason we would require to actually change that data framed frame or something like that
我们也可以通过更新缓冲区来做到这一点，那完全没问题
we can do that as well by just updating the buffer, and that's totally fine
但是现在，因为我们没有改变这些数据
but for now since of course we're not changing this data
你们可以看到我们的三角形没有变形成别的什么东西
you can see that our triangle is not morphing into something else or anything
它只是一堆静态顶点，我们可以在这个gl循环之外做那个
it's just a bunch of static vertexes, we can kind of do that outside of this gl loop
那么在这里，我要定义顶点缓冲区，这个过程很简单
so over here, I'm going to define my vertex buffer, and the way that this works is pretty simple
你们只需要输入glGenBuffers()，好了，然后指定你们想要多少个缓冲区
you just type in glGenBuffers(), Alright, then you specify how many buffers you would like
那么OpenGL可以一次生成一堆缓冲区，而我们只需要一个缓冲，所以就输入1
so OpenGL can generate you a bunch at once, we just want one buffer so I'm gonna type in one
然后第二个参数需要一个无符号整型指针
and then we need to give it a pointer at two, an unsigned int
你们可以在这里看到，这个函数返回void
you can kind of see here that this function returns void
所以函数不返回生成的缓冲区id，我们要给它提供一个整数（指针）
so instead of returning the id of what we generated, we instead provide it with an actual integer
然后函数把id写入这个整数的内存，那就是为什么这里需要一个指针
and it writes into that integer's memory, that's why this takes in a pointer
所以, 我要做的就是输入unsigned int，变量名为buffer
so what I can do is just type in unsigned int, I'll just call it buffer
然后传入这个unsigned int的内存地址，现在, 这就是生成的缓冲区的id
and then pass in the memory address of this unsigned int, now, what this is, is the id of the generated buffer
记住OpenGL作为一个状态机工作，这意味着，所有你们生成的……再说一次，这是与上下文相关的
remember OpenGL works as a state machine which means, everything you generate, again this is contextual
所以，我的意思是，上下文会有自己的流，缓冲区会有自己的流
so basically what I mean by that is, context will have kind of their own stream, buffers will have their own stream
但你们在OpenGL中生成的所有东西都会被分配一个唯一的标识符，它只是一个整数，比如0、1、2
but what, everything you generated in OpenGL gets assigned a unique identifier, it's just an integer, 0, 1, 2
0通常是一种无效状态，但不都是
0 is commonly kind of an invalid state, but not always
这也是你们以后需要学习的内容
so again something you need to learn which all of cover in the future
但基本上你们会得到一个数字，比如1、2、3等等，那是你们实际对象的id
but basically you get a number back like 1, 2, 3 whatever, and that's an id for your actual object
不管它是顶点缓冲区，顶点数组，纹理，着色器，或者其他任何东西
whether that be a vertex buffer, a vertex array, a texture, a shader, anything
对吧，你们都会得到一个整数，代表某种着色器
right, you get a number an integer back, which represents that specific shader
当你们想要使用这个对象的时候，就用这个数字，对吧
and then you basically just use that number whenever you want to use that object, right
所以如果我想绑定或选择我的缓冲区
so, if I want to bind or select my buffer
因为我要渲染我的三角形，并且需要说明用哪个缓冲区来渲染三角形
because I'm just about to render my triangle, and I need to specify which buffer to use to render my triangle
我只需要传递这个整数，它就像，嘿，你能像二号缓冲区描述的那样渲染吗
I just pass in that integer, it's like, hey, can you just like buffer No.2 please
那就是OpenGL的原理，所以，这就是这个，这里生成一个缓冲区，并返回它的id
that's how OpenGL works, so that's what this is, this is generating a buffer and giving us back an id
现在我们有了一个id，一旦创建缓冲区后，我们现在就要选择那个缓冲区
so now we have an id, once we've created an actual buffer we now need to select that buffer
并且选择(selecting)在OpenGL中称为绑定(binding)，所以我输入glBindBuffer()
and selecting in OpenGL called binding, so I just type in glBindBuffer()
第一个参数是目标，所以我已经生成了一个缓冲区，但是我要如何使用它呢
now this is the target, so I've generated a buffer, but how do I want to use it?
比如这些参数有什么意义，对我们来说，这只是一个内存缓冲区
like what is the purpose of all this,  for us, we literally this is just a buffer of memory
所以我们要用GL_ARRAY_BUFFER，也就是说这只是一个数组
so we're going to use GL_ARRAY_BUFFER,  which basically just says this is just an array
然后你们可能注意到了，我们传入了缓冲区的id，所以这个参数是我们要绑定的缓冲区
and then you can notice that we do pass in the id of the buffer, so this is the buffer that we're binding
当然，它就是我们刚生成的那个，到目前为止很简单
and of course it's the one that we've just generated, pretty simple so far
希望你们能坚持下去，所以下一步显然就是
hope you guys are keeping along with this, and so the next logical step is obviously to actually,
把数据放入这个缓冲区
well, put data into that buffer
你们可能已经注意到了，我没有具体说明这个缓冲区的大小
you may have noticed, that I haven't actually specified how large this buffer is or anything like that
我刚只是创建了一个缓冲区，然后绑定它（意味着我要使用这个缓冲区）
I've just created a buffer, and I've bound it, meaning that I'm just about to work on it
所以，实际上，下一步是指定数据，现在这儿有两种方式指定数据
so the next step is going to be to actually specify the data, now there's two ways you can do this
你们不需要马上给它提供数据，只需要指定……
you don't really have to provide it with data straight away, you just have to specify...
你们通常会在创建缓冲区时，指定它的大小
when you create a buffer you usually specify how large you want it to actually be
那么举个例子，比如200字节或之类的东西
so for example, I don't know, 200 bytes or something like that
然后你们可以直接给出数据
and then you have the option of straight away giving a data
或者你们可以不给它，之后再更新数据，那也挺不错的
or you can just give it nothing and then later update it with data, that's totally fine
由于我们明显地知道我们现在绘制的三角形
since we obviously know the triangle that we're drawing right now
我们可能就直接给它提供数据，所以键入glBufferData()
we might as well provide it with data straightaway, so I'm going to type in glBufferData()
然后，我们再次指定了目标GL_ARRAY_BUFFER
and then again we specify the target which is GL_ARRAY_BUFFER
这个大小是指我们希望这个缓冲区有多大，或者我们的数据有多大
the size meaning how big we want this buffer to actually be, or how big our data is
所以在这种情况下，我们来计算一下，这是所有的顶点
so in this case, let's kind of calculate this, we have all of these vertices here
现在我们用别的东西来声明它们，它们只是一堆数
let's actually declare them as something else, right now, they're just kind of numbers here
我们要创建一个包含所有这些数的float数组，对吧
let's make a float array which contains all of these, right
所以我要写float positions =，来创建一个数组
so I'm going to write float positions equals, and then we'll kind of make an array out of it
首先, 我要定义我想要多少，你们在C++中可以像这样（[ ]中空着）简单地定义数组
so first of all, I'll define how many I want, you can kind of just define arrays like this in C++
但我喜欢更具体一点
but I like to be a bit more specific
看到这有6个位置坐标，所以有6个顶点（数），所以我在这里写上6
so we know that we have six vertexes by looking at this six positions, so I'll just put in six here
然后我要指定它们，所以如果我向下滚动，复制这个
and then I'm actually going to specify them, so literally if I, scroll down here and copy this
按住alt+shift，然后按住从上到下拖
I'm holding alt shift and then clicking from the kind of the top to the bottom here
复制，粘贴，好了，我们有顶点的位置
ctrl c, ctrl v and there we go, we have our vertex positions
现在我喜欢把它们对齐，在这里，我们也需要一些逗号
now I like to kind of align them as well, we have to have commas here as well
但我想把它们对齐，在这里留个空格
but I like to align these so I just a space here
确保它们很好地对齐，这样我们就有了一个缓冲区
make sure they're nicely aligned and there we have a basic buffer
你们也可以把这个(positions数组)叫做缓冲区，对吧，因为这是一个连续内存数组
this is you could also call this the buffer, right, because there's an array of contiguous memory
在那个数组中，我们有6个浮点数，在这里，我们需要一个指定的大小
in which we have six floats, so over here, we're gonna need a specific size
现在因为这个数组是在堆栈上创建的，我可以输入sizeof(positions)
now because this array was created on the stack, I could just say sizeof(positions)
我真的不喜欢这么做（写sizeof()），所以我要做的替换，就是写6
I'm really not a fan of doing that there, so what I'm going to do instead, is just say six
因为有6个浮点数，所以就是6 * sizeof(float)
because we know that we have six floats times well, sizeof a float
所以需要注意的是，这个大小是指字节的大小，现在你们可能想知道
so it's important to note that this size is in bytes, now you might be wondering
我怎么知道它指的是字节，答案就是，好吧，当然是经验
how want do I know that it's in bytes, and the answer to that is, well, of course experience
但是你们也应该阅读文档，所以这是一个展示给你们看的好机会
but you also should be reading the documentation,  so this is a good chance for me to show you guys
这个我认为可能是OpenGL最好的文档网站，那就是docs.gl
what I think is probably the best documentation website for OpenGL, and that is docs.GL
所以我在下面的描述里放了一个链接(docs.gl)
so I've put a link to this in the description below
这里有OpenGL的大量文档资源
basically this is a huge kind of documentation resource here for OpenGL
它有很多OpenGL版本，包括嵌入式系统版本
it has a lot of OpenGL versions, including kind of the embedded systems versions
OpenGL的移动版本, 以及gl2,gl3和gl4
so the mobile versions of OpenGL, as well as gl2, 3 and 4
所以我们这里要做的就是输入函数的名称
so what we're going to do up here is just type in the name of our function
比如glBufferData，我要点击gl4
which is glBufferData, I'm going to click on gl4
因为我们用的就是这个版本，然后这里可以看到有两个重载
because that's the version that we're using, and then over here, you can see that there are two overloads
有一个叫glNamedBufferData，另一个叫glBufferData
while there's one called NamedBufferData and one called BufferData
显然这(glBufferData)是我们感兴趣的
obviously this is the one we're interested in
你们可以看到这是我们传入的size变量或参数
you can see there's our size variable or our size parameter that we're passing in
向下滚动，我们可以看看它的size，你们可以看到它说
this scroll down, we can look at the size and it's you can see that it says
指定缓冲区对象的新数据存储的字节大小，好了，你们还可以看到data
specifies the size in bytes of the buffer object's new data store, okay, and then you can see also for data
我们的下一个参数是一个指向data的指针
which is our next parameter specifies a pointer to the data
将被复制到数据存储区进行初始化的data
that will be copied into the data store for initializtion
如果没有data要复制，则为null，所以你们可以看到
or null if no data is to be copied, so you can see
通过阅读文档，有多容易知道如何使用它
just by reading the documentation, how easy it is to see how you can use this
比如现在我们知道可以传入null
like for example, we now know that we can just pass in null
如果我们一开始就不想给它提供任何数据
if we don't want to provide it with any data to begin with
这个usage参数也是很重要的东西，因此，它指定了想用的使用模式
the usage is also something that's important, so it specifies the expected usage pattern
所以带着这个想法，我想如果我们往下滚动，你们就可以看到……
so basically the idea with this, and I think if we scroll down here, you can see that there is
这个usage是对GL实现的一个提示，关于如何访问缓冲区对象的数据存储
the usage is a hint to the GL implementation, as to how a buffer's object's data store will be accessed
那么考虑到这点，我们可以在这里指定STREAM，STATIC和DYNAMIC三种
so with that in mind, we can specify STREAM, STATIC or DYNAMIC in here
这些意思是，STREAM意味着它将被修改一次，并且只能使用几次
which is basically STREAM means that it's going to be modified once and used at most a few times
STATIC意味着数据存储内容将被修改一次，并且能用很多次，对吧
STATIC means that the data store contents will be modified once and use many times, right
这实际上就是我们要那一种方式，我等会儿就会告诉你们
so that's actually the one we're laying towards, and I'll tell you one in a minute
最后是DYNAMIC，数据存储的内容会被反复修改，并且多次使用
and DYNAMIC, the data store contents will be modified repeatedly and use many times
所以，STATIC之所以很重要……说实话，STREAM并不经常使用
so the reason STATIC's important, STREAM is not something that we use too often to be honest
STATIC和DYNAMIC是我们比较关心的方式
STATIC and DYNAMIC are kind of the ones that we care about
STATIC意味着我们将会，它会被修改一次，然后使用多次
STATIC just means that we're going to be, it's going to be modified once and use many times
这意味着，你们可以看到，我们将创建这个buffer一次
what that means is, you can see that we're going to create this buffer once
我们不会每帧都修改buffer，但是我们要绘制每一帧
and we're not going to modify the buffer every frame, but we are going to draw it every frame
这就是“多次使用”的意思
so that's what it means by used many times
它会像这个三角形中的每一帧一样被绘制出来
it's going to be drawn like every frame in this case our triangle
而DYNAMIC是指
whereas DYNAMIC is something
数据存储的内容会被反复修改和多次使用
where the data store contents will be modified repeatedly and used many times
如果我们也修改这个三角形，每帧修改这些顶点
so if we were also modifying this triangle, modifying these vertexes every frame
并且每帧都会重绘，我们将使用DYNAMIC
and drawing it every frame, we would be using DYNAMIC
这些只是提示（意思是可以违反），这意味着是如果我声明它为STATIC，然后绘制它
now these are just hints, meaning that if I declare this a STATIC and then I draw it
但我实际上每帧都更新缓冲区，它还是会运行的，可能会慢很多
and then I update the buffer every frame, it's still gonna work, it's probably just gonna be a lot slower
记住这一点，这并不是一成不变的事情
so just keep that in mind, this isn't like a set in stone kind of thing
这只是一个提示，实际上，它在注释这儿说了，这个usage是GL实现的一个提示，好吧
it's just a hint in fact it says here in the notes, that usage is a hint to be GL implementation, okay
考虑到这一点，我们现在知道怎么填了
so with that in mind, we now know how to fill this out, hopefully
那么我们要提供的data指针指向这个positions数组
So, the data that we're going to provide it with is just going to be appointed to this positions thing
这已经不是数组了，当然，我们可以只写positions
now this is already isn't array, so of course, we can just write positions
那么，最后是GLenum usage参数，就是我们刚才讨论的usage
and finally GLenum usage, so that's the usage that we just talked about
我们想使用STATIC，所以这里就是GL_STATIC_DRAW
we want to use STATIC, so GL_STATIC_DRAW
现在我很少谈论绘制的事
now I didn't talk too much about the drawer thing
当然，我们会绘制出三角形，所以，DRAW也是我们关心的一个
but of course we will be drawing the actual triangles, so DRAW is the one that we care about
好了，很好，就是这样，我们为OpenGL指定了一些positions
okay, cool, so there we go, we've actually specified a bunch of positions for OpenGL and
这就是我们需要做的，通常，我们还需要创建一个索引缓冲区
that's really all we need to do, now, normally, we would also want to create something called an index buffer
我们会在以后的视频中讲这个
but we're gonna have another video about that in the future
因为我不想让这个视频太长
because I don't want to make this video too long
但现在理论上我们用这些数据能做的就是把它绘制出来
but basically what we can do now with this data theoretically is draw it now
不过我们还没有着色器，去解释如何用这些数据进行绘制
Now, we don't have a shader, to actually specify how the data has been drawn
我们将在下一期讨论那个问题
we're actually going to talk about that in the next episode
但是我们今天要做的，只是想看看，如果我们能不能把它绘制出来
but what we will do today is just to see if we can draw it anyway
我们需要什么代码来画这个（就好像我们已经有了一个着色器）
and we'll just see what the code required to draw this as if we did have a shader
那么回到这里，这就是我们用来给OpenGL传数据的所有代码
So back here, this is all the code we need to actually give OpenGL the data
然而，当我们给OpenGL数据时，我们并没有告诉它数据是什么
However, while we've given OpenGL the data, we haven't actually told it how... what the data is.
看这儿，这里写着
Remember, OpenGL is literally, if you kind of look at this
OpenGL接收一个数据指针，就是接收一堆字节
receiving a void pointer of data. It's receiving a bunch of bytes.
所以OpenGL到底是怎么知道的
now, how on earth is OpenGL supposed to know
如何正确解读这些字节，明白吧，它们只是一堆字节
how to interpret those bytes right, they're just a bunch of bytes
我们没有指定，嘿，已经给了你三个顶点
we haven't specified that, hey, we've given you three vertexes
它们都是浮点数，并且我们还给出了两个顶点位置，每个顶点，或两个……（这里在胡言乱语了）
they're floats and also we've given you two vertex positions, kind of per vertex, or two...
两个浮点数代表一个位置，就是一个顶点，对吧
kind of two floats represent one position which is a vertex, right
这些我们都没说过
we haven't said any of that
如果我们有纹理坐标，或法线，或其他东西，但它没有表达任何意义
What if we have texture coordinates, or normal, or other things and it doesn't make any sense
OpenGL不能像变魔术似的做到，比如，我知道你做了什么
OpenGL can't just magically be like, I see what you've done
你想让我绘制一个，两个……你指定了两个分量，或者两种坐标
you want me to draw a, two...you've kind of specified two component, or two kind of coordinates
你想让我用它们绘制一个三角形，不是这样的
and you just want me to draw a triangle with them, no, not how it works
实际上，我们需要告诉OpenGL，我们的数据是如何布局的
we need to actually tell OpenGL, how our data is laid out
这是我们绝对需要做的事情，因为从着色器的角度来看
and that is something that we definitely need to do, because remember from the shader side
我们希望能够以适当的方式读取这些数据
we want to be able to read this data in an appropriate way
比如这里这个顶点位置
for example, this kind of vertex position that we have here
我想理解成一个两个分量的向量，对，一个vec2
I'd love to just be able to read that as a two component vector, right, as a vector two
或者甚至可能是vec4
or maybe even a vector fourth
这样就可以用着色器把它与矩阵相乘，或者其他怎么样
so that I can multiply it with a matrix in my shader, or something like that
我们需要能够告诉OpenGL，我们的数据是如何布局的
we need to be able to tell OpenGL, how our data is laid out
我们可以用glVertexAttributePointer()函数来实现，对吧
and we can do that by using a function called glVertexAttributePointer, okay
那又是和着色器紧密联系在一起的东西，那么，我们今天先不讨论这个
now that is again something that is very closely tied with shader, so we're not going to talk about that today
但要把这个记住，我们还没准备好绘制
but just keep that in mind, we're not really ready to draw yet
但假如已经准备好了，那我们就来看一下，我要往下滑动
but if we were, let's take a look at that, so I'm going to scroll down over here
把这些垃圾删掉，腾出地方，我们使用立即模式画三角形
and instead of, having this junk here where we use, where we ran triangles using immediate mode
我实际上会为这个缓冲区发出一个DrawCall指令，并且我们的方法很简单
I'm actually going to issue a DrawCall for this buffer, and the way that we do that is very simple
主要有两种方法实现
there's two main ways of doing that
有个glDrawArrays()函数，这是一个没有索引缓冲区时可以用的方法
there's glDrawArrays() which is something that you do if you do not have an index buffer
因为我们没有索引缓冲区，所以就用这个方法了
and we don't have an index buffer so we'll look at that
你们可以看到，需要指定绘制的模式
you can see that we need to specify the mode that we're drawing in
这意味着，你们要画的是什么图元
What this means is, what kind of primitive are you trying to draw?
在这个例子中，我们要绘制一个三角形
in this case, we're trying to draw a triangle
所以我们输入GL_TRIANGLES，这个first参数，它只是一个偏移量
so we're just typing GL_TRIANGLES, the first, it's basically just an offset again
你们知道看看文档的，对吧，这些我都知道，但是为了你们好
you know documentation, right, I know all this, but for your sake
让我们一起来看看glDrawArrays到底做了什么，以及它的原理
let's go ahead and take a look atwhat glDrawArrays actually does and how it works
那么first参数，指定使用的数组中的起始索引
so first, specifies the starting index in the enabled array
所以换句话说，如果我们因为某种原因，我们想从第二个顶点开始
So in other ways, if we for some reason, we wanted to start from the second vertex
我们在这里输入1，对吧，因为我们从0开始数
we would type in one here, right, because we started zero
我们想要从顶点列表的起始位置开始，所以就写0
we do want to start from the beginning of our kind of list of vertexes, so I'm just going to write zero
然后，就是最后一个参数count，也就是要渲染的索引的数量
and then finally the count, which is the number of indices to be rendered
索引表示顶点，在这个例子中，我们有1个, 2个, 3个顶点
now indices kind of means vertexes, in this case, so, we have 1, 2, 3 of these
所以你们只需要输入3，理论上，如果我们按f5来运行程序
so you just type in three, and theoretically, if we hit f5 to run our program
你们会看到一个三角形
you would see a triangle
但是因为我们只写了大概30%的渲染三角形需要的代码
however since we've written like 30% of the code needed to render a triangle
所以，你们会看到一个黑屏，但大概就是这么回事
you'll see a black screen, but this is basically the idea
另一个DrawCall指令是glDrawElements()
the other DrawCall that we have is something called glDrawElements
这个是有索引缓冲区时使用的函数
which is something that we use with an index buffer
所以在这里，我们同样填GL_TRIANGLES，然后参数count，就是3
so in this case, we kind of specify the same thing GL_TRIANGLES, then the count so three
这个类型，实际上指的是索引数据的类型
the type which is actually the type of the index data
如果我们使用，如unsigned int或unsigned short，就把它放在这里
so if we're using like an unsigned int or an unsigned short, we would put that in there
最后一个参数是indices，那个我们几乎从不使用
and then finally appointed to the indices, which we almost never use
所以这通常填NULL，当我们讲到索引缓冲区的时候，我们再来讲这个
so that's usually just NULL, but again we'll look at that when we look at what index buffer is actually are
所以说，这就是DrawCall，对吧，这是实际绘制三角形的一行代码
so that being said that's the DrawCall, right, this is the line of code that actually draws our triangle
现在你们可能注意到它并没有指明任何东西
now you may notice here that it doesn't specify well anything
我的意思是它说它是一个三角形
I mean it says that it's a triangle
它从0开始，然后写了3
says it was starting at zero and went wrote three
它是怎么知道要画的是这一个呢，这就要回到我之前说的，OpenGL是一个状态机
how does it notice draw this one, and that comes back to me saying that OpenGL is a state machine
当我们写这段代码的时候，我们把这行代码写在这里，glBindBuffer()
when we were writing this block of code, and we wrote this code right over here, glBindBuffer
就是这行表明我们要绘制的是哪一个，绘制的就是当前绑定的那一个图形
that is what is going to be drawn, the one that is currently bound
如果在绘制之前（glDrawArrays()之前），我们没有绑定缓冲区，比如通过绑定0来实现
if before we did this, we bound no buffer, which you do by binding zero
这样就绘制不出我们的三角形了，因为我们选择了别的缓冲区
then this would not draw our triangle, because we've selected something else
我喜欢把这比作使用一个程序，比如photoshop
I like to compare this to using a program such as photoshop
当你们在photoshop中选择东西，如果我选择一个图层
when you select things in photoshop, if I select a layer
然后在该图层上用画笔绘制一些东西，它只会影响这一图层
and then draw something on that layer using the paintbrush, it's going to affect that layer
然而，如果我没有选择任何东西，或者选错了东西
however if I have nothing selected, or I have the wrong thing selected
很明显，它不会影响到我想绘制的那个图层，OpenGL也是一样
obviously it's not going to be affecting the layer that I want to draw on, OpenGL is the same
在使用它之前，你们需要选择或绑定所有东西
you need to select everything or bind everything before you actually do stuff with it
因为这就是它的运行原理，它是上下文相关的，它是一个状态机
because that's how it works, it's very contextual, it's a state machine
不论如何，希望大家喜欢这个视频，作为对顶点缓冲区的一点儿介绍
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video, as a bit of an introduction towards vertex buffers
我们还有很多东西要讲
we've still got a lot to cover
包括顶点属性，着色器和索引缓冲区对象
including kind of all the vertex attribute stuff, shader and index buffer kind of objects
这就是我们从本视频中得到的，我们需要做更多的工作
that's what we've kind of gathered from this video that we need to do a lot more work
但那是最基本的，希望你们喜欢这个视频
but that is the basics, hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧，请在下面的评论区留下你们的评论
if you did you can hit that like button, leave any comments you may have in the comment section below
如果你们想和更多的人谈论这些东西
if you want to talk about this stuff with a lot more people
你们可以通过thecherno.com/discord这个频道加入我的讨论
you can join my discord by going through thecherno.com/discord, and joining it
那里有很多人，我们整天都在谈论这些东西，所以这还是挺愉快的
there's a bunch of people there and we talk about this stuff all day long, so it's a good time
如果你们想帮助支持这个系列，想看更多内容
also if you want to help support this series, and you want to see more episodes
也可以一期接一期地看我在这些视频中写的所有源代码
as well as get access to all of the source code that I write in these videos episode by episode
那么你们可以在patreon上支持这个系列
then you can support this series on patreon
通过patreon.com/thecherno，也可以获取一些非常酷的奖励
by going to patreon.com/thecherno, get some pretty cool rewards
你们可能已经注意到了这些鼓舞人心的名单，就在视频的开头
you may have noticed the inspiring credits, at the beginning of the video
这是你们作为一个赞助人应该得到的，还有很多其他的东西
it's what you get by being a cool supporter, and there's a lot more kind of stuff
以及提前拿到这些视频，我觉得这很酷
as well as getting these videos early, which I think is pretty cool
不管如何，希望大家喜欢这个视频，下次见，再见
anyway, hope you guys enjoyed this video, and I will see you next time goodbye